I am so excited to be here
to talk about gaming.
There has been so many
changes in this industry
since I first started at Electronic Arts
almost 30 years ago.
I was very young, by the way, back then.
Now if you look
at these comparisons here,
our characters looked
more like 8-bit Laura, OK?
Today, they look more like 8K Laura.
And I must say, I kind of wish
I looked more like 8K Laura.
But that's not the point
I'm trying to make here right now.
The point really is,
is that graphic fidelity is one
of the most visible revolutions in games,
but there have been so many others.
Games have become social connection hubs,
and games are now synonymous
with pop culture.
I mean, take "Star Wars" as an example.
They have completely evolved
their narrative universe
based on over 10 games.
TV adaptations like "The Last of Us"
are winning Emmys for HBO.
And our own awards show,
The Game Awards,
had over 120 million viewers last year.
Now for some context,
if you take the Grammys,
the Oscars and the Emmys, times three,
it doesn't add up to how many viewers
we have in the Game Awards.
That's incredible.
(Applause)
Thank you, yes, good for gaming.
And this is good news for gaming.
But I'm here to tell you, I think
it's even better news for humanity.
In a world where
there's artificial intelligence,
artificial interactions,
having human connection is going to be
more important than ever.
And gaming is the perfect
medium to connect us.
AI and games have been synonymous
with each other from the beginning.
Remember those little ghosts in "Pac-Man?"
Little pixelated opponents in "Madden?"
Those may not seem very intelligent today,
but that was our start.
And today, AI, particularly generative AI,
is going to be an exponential
accelerator for making games,
for how players interact with games
and how they personalize
and create their own experiences.
But AI is not the only thing
driving change in the gaming industry
and in society in general.
Social media has transformed our lives.
I mean, think about it.
Hundreds of millions
of interactions and transactions daily.
Millions of followers, social platforms.
You would think we are more
connected than we've ever been,
but that's not the case.
I mean, left to our own devices,
well, we have been left
to our own devices.
And there's emerging evidence to say
that there's a trend happening
that the surgeon general is calling
an “epidemic of loneliness.”
The data says that people
are having a hard time
making and keeping friends,
more than ever.
I mean, this is scary stuff.
We all know that belonging to a community
and having a sense
of belonging to each other
is critical to our mental well-being.
But don't worry,
I'm here to tell you
that games are going to save us.
Games bring people together.
That's what I love about them.
They're creative, they're fun.
I mean, take a look at this video here
of this incredibly fun gameplay.
People are creating together, sharing,
expressing themselves, collaborating.
This is what gaming can do.
Games have always been my choice of media.
Now I love a great movie and reality TV
as much as the next person,
but nothing lights up your brain
like a great game
and interactive entertainment.
I mean, even the
World Health Organization,
after years of skepticism about gaming,
has come out to espouse
the benefits of gaming.
This was a massive turning point
in public perception.
It also spawned a lot of research
around the benefits of gaming,
including the power of play in 2023,
where they surveyed 13,000 respondents
in 12 countries
to validate what many of us know,
that gaming helps with critical skills,
critical thinking,
judgment, collaboration.
But what I found most interesting
was that 55 percent of the respondents
said they play games
to not feel alone or isolated.
And I get it.
I play games to not feel alone.
And some of the happiest
moments of my life
I was in isolation.
About 20 years ago,
my husband and I welcomed twins.
Oh, thank you, I know, they were so cute.
That was 20 years ago.
(Laughter)
They don't look like that anymore.
But we were so excited
and so happy about this.
But we were homebound
for the first time in our lives.
We quickly realized that the best way
for social connection
with our friends and family
and, dare I say, even each other,
was through gaming.
We quickly joined a family guild,
and we played "World of Warcraft"
for the first several years
of our kids' lives.
Now I love most games,
and I do, I love to play games.
But nothing beats playing together.
And people who play games
together play for longer.
Studies also show
that people who play games
and collaborate in games
are actually more collaborative
and more cooperative outside of games.
That's pretty remarkable.
Now when I first started in the industry,
I started a company called
Westwood Studios.
And I was responsible
for our online community.
And we had -- this is back in 1996.
We had -- wait for it --
one million players in our community,
which was huge back then.
It was huge.
I thought we were really hot stuff.
Fast forward to today,
we have 700 million players
in the network at EA.
That's more than double
the population of the US.
Incredible number.
But the magic number
isn't actually 700 million.
The magic comes when you play
with three to five other people.
And we call this your atomic network.
And it's no accident that the atomic
number is actually three to five.
There's a really interesting study
that Colorado State University did
with 6,000 respondents about loneliness.
And what we know
is that people, on average,
for history, and now, today,
people on average have
about four to five friends always.
But today, the difference is
people feel far less connected
than they ever have,
and they're longing for connection
and to do things together.
Now another dimension
of gaming that I love
is that you can get
to know each other playing games.
Your personality and your skills
are on full display when you play a game.
Now let’s face it,
most of us are not going to make it
as a Navy SEAL in the real world,
but that’s why games are so much fun.
You can roleplay this, right?
So imagine, if you will, your squad
is dropped into a remote location,
you're fighting for survival,
you're strategizing on the fly,
all while the clock ticks away.
Another good use of gaming
could be compatibility test.
Now would I have married my husband
if he wasn't such an upstanding
guild member of "World of Warcraft"?
(Laughter)
We'll never know.
And he doesn't know I included that photo.
So, sorry, honey, hello.
(Laughter)
Now you may be in an atomic network now,
or you may be looking for one.
There are billions of gamers
out there playing games.
You can join "Fortnite,"
"Minecraft," "The Sims," "FC."
The list is long.
And sure, you might get
chirped in the chat,
but you also might meet
the love of your life.
So many people are ready to play.
They're ready to enter
epic worlds, epic adventures,
meet amazing people.
I really believe
that games are the superior
social platform of the future.
They’re immersive, active, engaging
and overwhelmingly fun.
So yes, social media,
technology, particularly AI,
are going to drastically change our future
and particularly the relationships
that we have with each other.
So being intentional
and maintaining human connection
through games
is an amazing path through.
So this is a call to arms.
Stop scrolling,
pick up your game controller,
jump into an epic world,
live an amazing story
and go on an exciting adventure
with three to five
of your closest friends.
It could just unite us all.
Thank you.
(Applause)
Manoush Zomorodi:
I have a question, come over here.
Talk to me about the hardware.
Where do you see that progressing?
I mean, we see people
putting things on their heads.
Are they going to be put,
I don't know, chips, brains.
Talk us through what you see.
Laura Miele: Chips and brains,
toasters, refrigerators,
you can game everywhere.
There's already a broad spectrum
of accessibility to game
and interactive experiences today,
and that's only going to expand
significantly as time goes on.
And what I love about gaming
is how vast that spectrum actually is.
And I think the future will still --
you can still pick up your mobile device,
play word puzzles with friends
to, fast forward, put on,
to your point, goggles, glasses,
and you know, you saw
the Navy SEAL footage
from the game called "Battlefield."
You will feel like you are actually
in that landscape and in those worlds,
it will be super immersive
and super connected,
which I think is only going
to continue to help us feel
like we can connect on a human level.
So I'm really excited
and optimistic about it.
MZ: OK, looking forward to that.
Laura, thank you so much.
LM: Thanks, Manoush.
(Applause)