There's not a lot in this world
that we can be truly certain about.
But I'm willing to guarantee
that most of us in this room
have seen this little blue dog before.
(Laughter)
This little dog is, of course,
the star of the global smash hit
children's show "Bluey,"
created and founded
right here in Brisbane.
The show also takes place here,
with the iconic skyline and sights
visible as we follow
the adventures of the Heeler family.
Bluey, a primary school-aged
blue heeler dog,
her little sister Bingo,
their dad Bandit and their mum Chilli.
Each bite-sized, seven-minute
episode offers a slice of life,
delving into valuable life lessons
and the nuances of parenting
through a playful lens
of childhood imagination.
Since the show's debut in 2018,
"Bluey" has taken the world by storm.
The international success in particular
is unlike any Australian
media of its kind.
In fact, "Bluey" is so popular
that there are countless videos
of kids in other countries
pronouncing things like "no,"
(Laughter)
and "mum" in little Australian accents.
But what if I told you that the show
isn't just a hit with kids?
Evidently, I am not a child.
(Laughter)
Nor do I have any kids yet.
But let me tell you,
I have spent hours laughing,
crying, questioning life,
just being captivated by cartoon dogs.
(Laughter)
And it isn't just me.
You might be surprised to see
that this "Adult Bluey Fans"
Facebook group
has more than 600,000 members.
(Laughter)
Then there’s the “Bluey” subreddit
with over 200,000.
And Bluey is also Insta-famous
with 1.3 million followers.
It's no secret,
older audiences love "Bluey."
Which really got me thinking.
I mean, there has to be
something more going on here
because, well, no offense
to the average three-year-old,
but you wouldn't find me
watching something like "Peppa Pig"
or "Cocomelon" in my free time.
So what is it about "Bluey"
that draws in older audiences?
The show's creator, Joe Brumm,
has spoken openly about his goal
of creating something
that parents and carers
can genuinely enjoy
rather than just tolerate.
And there are definitely parts of the show
that feel like they were put in
for the adults watching,
which isn't a new thing.
I mean, we've all seen
something like "Shrek"
and been kind of astonished
by some of the things
that they slipped in there.
But what I love about "Bluey's"
adult subtext, we'll call it,
is that its objective
isn’t always being crude or cheeky
but being relatable.
And one of the most
relatable moments of "Bluey"
are the scenes where we see
the back seat of the family car.
I can see so much
of my own childhood in this image,
and I bet a lot of you watching
have had a car that looks
a lot like that one.
Like most children's shows,
"Bluey" episodes appear to be centered
around some kind of life lesson.
There's the classic,
listen to your parents,
eat your veggies,
get back on the bike when you fall down.
But then there are lessons like,
work-life balance is important.
Raising kids isn't easy,
sometimes you'll make mistakes.
Aging can be daunting,
and your health means everything.
Not quite what you'd expect
from a kids' show, is it?
There's no shortage
of moral teachings for kids
and for adults.
In particular, the show portrays adulthood
in a way that's realistic and nuanced.
We see the adult characters
making mistakes, getting emotional,
learning all kinds
of lessons of their own.
You can imagine how reassuring
that would feel for a first-time parent
or a teenager heading into adulthood.
In the episode "Baby Race"
Chilli, the mom,
speaks openly about her experience
with overthinking parenting
and comparing herself
to the other moms around her.
She says she’ll never forget
receiving a visit from her friend Bella,
a mother of nine
who's learnt a thing or two.
Bella listens to Chilli's troubles
and tells her, “There’s something
you need to know:
You're doing great."
These words are spoken
to Chilli on screen,
but they aren't meant only for her ears.
And it's interactions like these
that set "Bluey" apart
from the average kids' media.
The show openly engages
with its older viewers,
not only acknowledging their presence
but often communicating directly to them.
The level of dimension and authenticity
in "Bluey's" stories and characters
is exceptional.
The writers haven't shied away
from portraying disabilities
and neurodivergence
and have even touched
on things like anxiety, divorce,
infertility, bullying
and death.
The show's received a lot of praise
for its portrayal of these
more substantial themes,
in a way that is still digestible
and meaningful for its younger audience.
It can prompt adults
to have conversations with kids
about things that they might
not have come across before.
It could also help a child
understand their own experience
if they're going
through something similar.
There's an authenticity in the way
that "Bluey" incorporates very important,
real aspects of life,
with an appropriate balance
of fun and lightheartedness
that you'd expect from a cartoon.
This authenticity has resonated
with younger and older viewers alike.
The show captures a quintessential
childhood experience,
evoking a rich sense of nostalgia
in its older viewers,
especially for Australians,
seeing the crows and bin chickens
hanging around the rubbish.
Or watching Bluey and Bingo
get a sausage and bread
at their local hardware store.
Look familiar?
But you don't need to be Australian
to appreciate "Bluey."
There's such a true-to-life
portrayal of imagination and play
with themes of school
and friends and growing up,
which makes the show so nostalgic.
There are so many games and rhymes
and dance moves that nobody
even remembers learning.
Every kid just seems to know.
And "Bluey" incorporates these stunningly.
The human brain is hard-wired
to crave that nostalgia.
It makes us feel good, warm inside.
From a psychology standpoint,
adults often turn to things like nostalgia
and childlike activities
as a form of escapism,
transporting our minds
back to a simpler time
to step away from the pressures
of daily life for a little while.
And there's good reason for this.
As we grow up, life tends
to become a lot less whimsical.
There's very little room
in our adult world
for make-believe and pretend,
and the way that we use our imaginations
becomes a lot more practical
and a lot less playful.
For me, I'm not sure exactly when,
but one day I stopped
believing in the fairies
that were living in the garden.
And now if I fall asleep in the car,
I don't wake up magically in my bed.
I just wake up with a weird neck.
So the ability to escape for a moment,
to re-experience some
of that long-lost childhood magic
through the lens of "Bluey"
has provided a lot of comfort
and wholesomeness that's really
touched people's hearts.
Some adult fans who lived
through difficult childhoods
have described watching "Bluey"
as therapeutic and healing.
They find that it offers them a chance
to vicariously experience the safe,
warm and positive environment
that the characters are growing up in.
It's also worth noting that "Bluey's"
skyrocket into stardom
sort of coincided
with the COVID-19 pandemic.
As the demand for at-home
entertainment for children surged,
a lot of grown ups also found themselves
turning to things like cartoons
and nostalgic media
as a way of getting
through the worst of the pandemic.
People can be particularly drawn
to escapism during tough times.
And in the last few years,
a beautiful cartoon about a family of dogs
has become a beacon of solace
for many of us.
So relatability, authenticity,
nostalgia and comfort.
There is one more key element
that draws adult viewers
into the world of "Bluey,"
and that is ...
The show's profound ability
to introduce new perspectives.
For a lot of us grown-ups,
we have a responsibility to teach
and nurture the little ones in our lives.
But equally,
there is so much
that we can learn from them.
Children approach the world
with an innate sense of wonder.
They always seem to find enjoyment
and novelty in the mundane.
And if it isn’t there,
they will create it.
To Bluey and Bingo, that isn't
just a swing, it's a cocoon.
"Let's play butterflies."
That piece of cardboard
looks like a volcano.
"I know, let's pretend we're dinosaurs."
Anything can be a game.
Anything can be new and exciting and fun.
A lot of us adults, with our serious lives
and our developed frontal lobes,
could do with a reminder of that.
Kids teach us to do a silly walk
to spice up the housework,
throw a sticky gecko toy at the ceiling
and wait for it to fall down.
Make friends with a stranger,
dance in public,
save a caterpillar's life.
They teach us to approach the world
with curiosity and hope and playfulness.
And above all,
they teach us not to take
ourselves too seriously.
(Laughter)
"Bluey" has grown a devout audience
of children,
teenagers
and adults.
And that's thanks to its
relatability and authenticity,
as well as the comfort
and perspective that it has to offer.
With its dimensional
stories and characters
against a backdrop
of vibrant Australian imagery,
"Bluey" really is more
than just another cartoon for kids.
So next time you find yourself
interacting with a child
or watching one
of their TV shows or movies,
remember that there may be something
much deeper at play.
And keep an eye out for all the weird
and wonderful things
that you can learn from little humans
and little blue dogs.
Thank you.
(Applause)