Picture a boardroom in China.
What do you see?
Well, big changes are coming.
In the next decade,
you will start to see much younger
faces filling up these spaces.
I'm not just talking about China's
international giants.
I’m talking about China’s small-
and medium-sized local businesses.
With 100 to 500 million
US dollars in revenue.
There are local giants in beverage,
snacks or fashion.
As we speak,
there are 50-, 60- and
70-year-old founders
who are getting ready
for a boardroom transition.
And a whole new generation
will rise to power.
Why does this matter, you might ask.
Because competition is only
about to get fiercer in China,
and the new masterminds
behind these businesses
are also eager to take their family
businesses onto the global stage.
I live in China.
I spent the last 10 years
consulting with Chinese companies,
and I've worked with over 50 chairpersons.
From my conversations with them
and the broader data,
I can tell you that those local players
are gradually gaining market share
across many industries.
So why are these local companies
suddenly more competitive?
One big reason is that these new leaders
look nothing like their parents.
They grew up with greater
access to the internet.
They left China to study business
in the US, the UK, Australia,
Canada and Singapore.
They are multilingual.
They have advanced degrees.
They can tap into their vast networks
of professional services,
private equity and venture capital.
And now they are coming home
to take over their family businesses,
catapult them onto the world stage
and change the face
of business in China forever.
Here is what you can expect.
Number one, fewer copycats
and more innovation.
In the 1970s and '80s,
many entrepreneurs were cash-strapped.
To succeed fast,
let's just say imitation
was the sincerest form of flattery.
If you saw someone selling energy drink,
you'd launch your own energy drink.
However, this new generation knows
that copycatting is a dead-end model.
They are figuring out
how to kickstart innovation in-house
through competition.
For example,
I worked with a snack company
who was struggling with sluggish sales.
Their research and development
process was just not working.
They developed a lot of new flavors
but nothing truly innovative.
Until the second generation came up
with a surprising idea.
They split this large R and D team
into two smaller teams
to compete against each other.
The team with the winning product
would get a share of profits.
When one of the teams
talked with their consumers,
they realized there is an unmet need.
Their beef jerky packaging
was difficult to open,
and the beef was too long and too tough.
The consumer felt self-conscious
eating it in public or at work.
So the team redesigned the packaging
and made the jerky smaller and softer.
This design won the blind test
and was launched to the market,
where it enjoyed great sales,
especially in the company's
original flavor jerky.
And the winning team got
five percent of all the profits
that exceeded the original target.
Since the new generation
launched this new system,
new products have generated
over 40 percent
of the company's annual sales revenue.
Number two,
smart investments in bold ideas.
Many first-generation entrepreneurs
in China succeeded through grit,
through experience and through
keen market intuition.
They didn't have an MBA
or professional team to fall back on.
When it came to making big decisions,
they often went with their gut.
Of course, failure wasn't
a bad teacher either,
but this new generation can think
like an objective investor.
I worked with a plant-based
beverage company
whose founder had always sold
their drinks to restaurants,
never direct to consumer.
But when COVID hit the restaurants,
their sales plummeted.
The second generation knew
they needed a change,
even if change was hard.
So she first founded
an investment committee
and then announced open auditions
to fund new business ideas.
The winning idea would get funding,
but financial performance
would be quarterly reviewed
by the investment committee.
One sales manager suggested
switching from large glass bottles
to smaller paper carton packaging.
They'd market them to mothers
as a nutritious breakfast drink
with kid-friendly flavors
like sesame, like jasmine.
When it launched, within three months,
the new drink ranked
into the top three plant-based milks
on major e-commerce platforms.
With this investor mindset,
the new generation is helping team members
become the CEO of their own ideas.
And number three,
businesses will expand
into the entire ecosystem.
In an age of scarcity,
first-generation entrepreneurs
focused on doing one thing
and doing it right.
But the new generation
grew up with internet giants
who have built massive digital ecosystems:
vast interconnected
networks of e-commerce,
logistics, social media, payment, etc.
They don't just do one thing,
they do nearly everything.
I worked with a livestock producer
whose founder focused on rearing
the highest quality pork and poultry,
and they were very successful.
But the second generation is thinking
way bigger than raising livestock.
It's only the first step
in a very long value chain.
What if they expanded downstream?
They could get into meat processing
and develop their own line of sliced ham,
sausage and jerky.
They could even invest in companies
that buy their meat products,
like dumpling brands.
By thinking about the entire ecosystem,
from farming to food and even to retail,
they can simplify the supply chain,
spend less, earn more and expand faster.
All three of these examples
show what's possible
when the future second-generation leaders
take over Chinese businesses.
They’re not just looking to imitate
but to create and lead
their own ecosystems
and be bullish on every
growth opportunity.
These new leaders don't shy away
from competition.
In fact, they embrace it
and push change vertically and laterally.
And they don't take no for an answer.
To compete internationally,
we might even see a new wave
of major multinational companies
emerge from China.
So don't be surprised
when China's boardrooms have
a lot less gray hair in the coming years.
China's future has never
looked more colorful.
Thank you.