How do you feel about going to work?
Excited to start the day
or kind of dreading it?
We've been hard-wired to believe
that work isn't supposed to be enjoyable.
Work is work.
But here's the thing.
In the future,
companies will succeed or fail
based on how much
their people enjoy their work.
Now, when I tell that to business leaders,
a lot of them say, "That's great, Rosie,
but it's the end of fiscal quarter
and the CEO is breathing down my neck
because the board
is breathing down her neck
because our stock price is dropping.
Let's talk about enjoying work
once we're in a better spot.
Or never."
Now I get it.
These leaders are right
to fixate on business performance.
But I've spent the past six years
exploring this topic
as a people and organization
expert at BCG,
and the data is clear.
Making work more enjoyable
pays off big time.
Just look at the top 100 companies
to work for in America.
Over the last 28 years,
their stock returns
were more than double their peers'.
So instead of asking
how can we boost productivity,
these leaders should be asking,
how can we boost enjoyment?
Productivity and profit will follow.
So here are my top three tips
to make work more enjoyable.
Tip one: double down on joy.
Ask yourself, "What do I enjoy
most about my work?
And how can I do more of that?"
Take Trader Joe's,
an American grocery store
with a cult following.
If you've been to a Trader Joe's,
you know it just feels
different shopping there.
Every employee seems genuinely
happy to see you.
They want to know
what you're doing this weekend
and whether you've tried
these pumpkin spice Joe-Joe's.
It's almost surprising how happy they seem
in a stereotypically low-paying,
high-turnover retail job.
So how does Trader Joe's do it?
Well, they know that the fun part
of working in retail
is chatting up your co-workers
and the customers.
So they've created
this super social environment
by purposefully overstaffing their stores.
The result?
Overstaffing means employees
enjoy their work more,
are less likely to feel burnt out,
and are less likely to consider quitting.
In fact, one in 10 Trader Joe's employees
has worked there for over a decade,
which is pretty crazy
when you consider how expensive it is
to replace an employee,
not to mention the lost productivity
as they learn how to do the job.
But overstaffing doesn't
just save Trader Joe's money,
it makes them more money, too.
Employees have more time to interact
with customers and drive spending.
If you compare Trader Joe's to its peers,
they make 50 percent
higher revenue per employee.
So doubling down on joy
is good for employees,
customers and shareholders alike.
And it didn't require expensive
pay rises or fancy bonuses.
Yes, you need to pay
your employees a living wage,
but don't make the mistake of thinking
more enjoyment only means more money.
It doesn't.
We all know people
who make a ton of money
and still loathe their jobs.
So get creative.
Figure out what it is that you
enjoy most about your work
and do more of that.
Tip two: eliminate frustrations.
My second tip is the opposite.
Ask "What's most frustrating
about the work I do
and how can I do less of that?"
Back in 2020,
US department store Neiman Marcus
was in pretty dire straits.
Employees were quitting at record rates,
the pandemic had closed
nearly all their stores
and by May they were filing
for bankruptcy.
To survive, they needed to make
some serious changes.
So they created an option
for store associates
to serve customers remotely
as work-from-home digital stylists.
But here's where things get
really interesting.
When the world reopened post-pandemic,
Neiman Marcus could have easily gone back
to their old ways of working.
But they know from extensive surveys
that flexibility is their employees'
number one concern.
So while other companies
were issuing return-to-work mandates,
Neiman Marcus doubled down
on flexible work.
Now, a store associate might spend
some three days a week in-person
behind the makeup counter
and two days working from home,
serving online shoppers.
With more people shopping online,
it's a win for customers,
employees and the company.
Staff turnover has dropped by 20 percent.
So if you want people
to perform at their best,
ask what's getting in their way
and then design the work
to minimize those frustrations.
Tip three: keep experimenting.
My final tip is to revisit
enjoyment repeatedly.
What works well today,
might not work a month down the line.
In my job, our teams take a weekly survey
about whether we're enjoying our work.
And then we review the results together.
But we don't spend it poring over
pie charts and line graphs.
We make it fun by asking questions like,
"Which one of these nine kangaroos
represents how this week went for you?"
And someone might say,
“Well, I started out this week
as the snuggly joey,
safe and sound in his mother's pouch.
But then I had a really
atrocious client meeting
and felt kind of hung out to dry.
So by the end of the week,
I was like the more feral,
possibly rabid kangaroo."
It might sound like a silly process
for such a serious task,
but it works.
We've come up with so many ways
to make work more enjoyable,
like shifting a morning check-in
30 minutes later
so that a team member can drop
his kid off at kindergarten.
A trivial change for us
that made the world of difference to him.
So make a habit of talking
about enjoying work,
and you'll come up
with surprising solutions
that make work
more enjoyable for everyone.
So before you get back to whatever
it was that you were doing
before you tuned into this talk,
I'd love for you to ask,
how can I enjoy this more?
Because what's enjoyable for you
is good for your company too.
Thank you.