We live in an incredible
time of exploration,
on the verge of finding out
whether we are alone in the cosmos or not.
This is one of the biggest questions
humankind has ever asked.
And now, for the first time,
we have a tool that could find out.
Because the James Webb Space Telescope
is a telescope large enough
to be able to catch light
from planets like ours,
as small as ours, but circling
other stars light-years away.
Because this search is a search
over vast cosmic distances,
even light needs years
to travel these trillions
of miles between stars.
So when you look up at the sky at night,
you look back in time.
Let's imagine you were on a planet
circling our neighboring star,
about four light-years away.
Then you would see the Earth
tonight, like it was four years ago.
On a planet 70 million light-years away,
you could still see
the dinosaurs roam here.
And it also means that out in the sky,
there is a star
whose light arrives tonight,
that was sent out when you were born.
Your personal connection to the cosmos.
So these distances are vast,
but astronomers, throughout time,
have managed to unravel
and reveal mysteries of the cosmos,
because light and matter interact.
So light carries energy,
and if it hits a molecule
with just the right energy,
that molecule will start
to swing and rotate.
So it's really the missing light,
the light that doesn't make
it to my telescope,
that tells me which molecules
the light encountered before it got to me.
It's a little bit like a passport stamp
that tells you where a traveler was
before arriving here.
So when you look at this incredible
image of the Pillars of Creation
taken by the James Webb Space Telescope,
it is gorgeous.
But if you analyze the light,
you realize that we are watching
a stellar nursery,
where we see stars emerge and ignite.
And when you look at stars
in our night sky,
you reveal another astonishing truth --
that you and me, all of us,
are made of ancient stardust.
Because it took the heat
in the core of a star
and the violent explosion
at the end of its lifetime
to make the atoms that made you and me.
So on a fundamental level,
we are connected to each other
and to the cosmos around us.
And now, for the first time,
we get to search
for other organisms somewhere else
that might be made
of ancient stardust, too.
But when you try
to find life in the universe,
it is incredibly hard,
because planets are so much smaller,
and they are close
to their bright and big stars.
And we don’t only want
to find planets like ours,
we want to look in their air
and on their surface for signs of life.
So what we do is we wait
until the planet crosses
our line of sight to its star,
and the light from its star hits,
smashes into the atmosphere of the planet
before it gets to my telescope.
So I can look for these passport stamps
to figure out what's in the air
of planets very far away,
and the light fingerprint.
The best light fingerprint
we have for life on the Earth
is the combination of oxygen and methane
for carbon-based life,
with a water solvent,
on a planet in the temperate zone
around its star.
But I was really curious:
How long could this light fingerprint
tell you that there’s life on our planet?
And so I figured out that,
for about two billion years,
the biosphere has painted signs
of life into our atmosphere.
So for half of Earth's existence,
you could tell that there is
life on our planet.
And if life does this somewhere else too,
for the first time,
we have now a chance to spot it.
And so searching for life in the universe
actually made me see our planet
completely differently.
Here, for example, you see biota
that colors these amazing
hot sulphur springs in New Zealand
this gorgeous orange color,
and it lets you start to think
about how different
these other planets could be.
There could be could be planets
completely covered in oceans,
with waves that never break on a shore.
Or planets half in eternal sunlight
and half in perpetual night.
Or planets that are covered
with a purple landscape.
Because purple bacteria is very sturdy,
it can thrive under red sunlight.
So eight out of ten stars out there
are actually small red stars.
So purple might be the new green,
when searching for life in the cosmos.
But we know that one
out of five sun-like stars
has a planet that could
potentially be like ours.
So with 200 billion stars
in our Milky Way alone,
that means we have billions
and billions of possibilities.
I founded the Carl Sagan
Institute at Cornell
to bring thinkers and creative minds
from many different fields and backgrounds
and ways of life together
to create the toolkit
to find life in the cosmos.
And so we created a spectral database,
a light-fingerprint database
for habitable worlds.
And in case you're wondering,
actually, Jurassic worlds,
where space dinosaurs
might roam somewhere else,
are actually easier to find
than a modern Earth,
because there was more oxygen
when the dinosaurs lived here.
I'm not saying there are space dinosaurs,
but I'm just saying if you ever wanted
there to be, I'm giving you options.
(Laughter)
But when you search,
then one of the questions that came
was also if there's life in the cosmos.
Of course, I don't know that yet.
But if there's life in the cosmos,
could somebody be looking at us
with just the same technology we have?
And there's a space in the sky,
a strip where you have
just the right vantage point
to see the Earth go in front of the Sun.
And it encapsulates about 1,000 stars
within 300 light-years,
what's really our cosmic background.
And so the question is,
where could we be the aliens?
Is there life in the cosmos?
I don't know.
We don't know yet,
but I really want to find out,
because the cosmos
is 13.8 billion years old,
but we all get to live
in the most exciting time,
where the search for life on other planets
went from impossible to possible.
And it's at the edge
of technical capability,
but we're already designing
larger telescopes
that could catch more light
of these planets
to find out if there’s life out there
calling another planet home.
From a tiny town in Austria,
when I looked up at the stars
and wondered if they could
be suns to their planets,
to now sitting in Carl Sagan's
old office at Cornell,
the journey has been
challenging, inspiring
and full of wonder,
because those thousands of new stars,
new suns [in] the sky,
hold a breathtaking promise
that our adventure of exploration
has just begun.
So go out at night
and find your favorite star,
and allow yourself to wonder,
what if we're not alone?
Thank you.
(Cheers and applause)