So today, what I want to do
is talk to you about the most important
conversations you have each day:
the conversations
you have with yourselves.
My name is Ethan Kross.
I’m the director of the
Emotion and Self Control Lab
at the University of Michigan,
and for the past 25 years,
I've been studying how people
can manage their emotions.
And one of the things that I've learned
during that time -- (Object drops)
See? I'm managing my emotions right now.
(Laughter)
One of the things
that I've learned during that time
is that a key to managing
one's emotions effectively
involves understanding
how to harness this mysterious force
called the voices inside our head.
Now I realize some of you
may be asking yourself right now,
“What is a purported
serious scientist doing
talking about a squishy topic
like the voices inside our head?"
But I want to point out
the elephant in the room --
that, you know, if you've just asked
yourself that question,
you are talking to yourself.
And that's totally OK,
because the vast majority of us
have a voice inside our head.
Here's a scientific fact
that I absolutely love.
We spend between one half and
one-third of our waking hours
not focused on the present.
Between one half
and one-third of the time,
our minds, they are drifting away.
We are thinking about other things.
Some of you are doing that right now.
Please stop.
(Laughter)
Once we find ourselves drifting away,
one of the things that we're doing
is talking to ourselves
and listening to what we say.
Now when scientists like myself
use the term “inner voice,”
what we're talking about
is our ability to silently use language
to reflect on our lives.
And it turns out this is one
of your superpowers,
because your inner voice lets you keep
information active in your head
for short periods of time,
like when you go to the grocery store.
And if you're like me,
15 seconds into the expedition,
you forget what you’re supposed to buy,
and you repeat that list in your head.
"Apples, cheese. Pepto Bismol."
TMI.
We also use our inner voice
to simulate and plan,
like when we silently rehearse
what we're going to say
before an important presentation
or an interview.
And of course, we use our inner voice
to control and motivate ourselves,
as I did just before I came on stage.
It's right around the corner, over there.
I silently said to myself, "Come on, man,
you've got this. Deep breath.
45 minutes, and you are done.”
(Laughter)
And of course, all of you
just said to yourself,
"This guy thinks he's talking
for 45 minutes. He's nuts."
(Laughter)
Finally, perhaps most magically,
we use our inner voice to make sense
of this messy world that we often live in.
When we experience challenges,
we turn our attention inward,
and we try to work through them.
And our inner voice
helps us create those stories
that shape our sense of self,
stories that really craft our identity.
So your inner voice,
this is a remarkable tool.
The problem is it is a tool that often
jams up on us when we need it most.
We don't come up with clear
solutions to our problems.
We get stuck in negative
thought loops, instead.
We worry. We ruminate.
We experience what I call the dark side
of our inner voice: chatter.
How do you know
if you're experiencing chatter?
If you ever find yourself
trying to work through a problem
but not making any progress,
or if you find yourself
berating yourself incessantly --
"I'm an idiot, such an idiot."
Those are two telltale signs.
Now if this description of chatter
resonates with any of you here --
I'm sure it does not.
But if it does,
my response to you is welcome
to the human condition, my friends.
Chatter is a feature of it.
We all have the capacity
to experience it at times.
It also happens to be
one of the big problems
we face as a species.
And I say this because,
if you look at what chatter does to us,
it sinks us in three domains of life
that I would argue everyone here
cares a great deal about.
One thing that chatter does,
it makes it really hard
for us to think and perform.
If you've ever had the experience
of sitting down to read
a few pages in a book,
and under oath, you would swear to a judge
that you have read the words
on the screen or page,
but you get to the end
of the section, the chapter,
and you don't remember
a damn thing that you've read,
you've experienced one way
that chatter undermines us.
It consumes our attention,
leaving very little left over
to do the things that we often
want and need to do.
Chatter also creates friction
in our relationships with other people,
because when we experience chatter,
we're often highly motivated
to share its glory with those around us.
What I mean by that is we often
want to talk about our chatter,
so we find someone to talk to,
and then, we keep on talking,
over and over again.
This can have a really sad consequence
of pushing away people
who genuinely care about us,
because there's only so much
that they can endure
before we start to bring them down.
Then there's our health.
So chatter helps explain
how stress gets under our skin
to impact our physical health,
because what it does
is it prolongs our stress response.
And that creates a wear and tear
in our body that is physically damaging,
predicts things like problems
of cardiovascular disease, inflammation,
even certain forms of cancer.
Now when people hear about these findings,
the question they often ask me is:
“How can I silence this inner voice?
Just shut it up."
And I don’t think this is the best
question to be asking.
Because your inner voice
is a remarkable tool.
We don't want to get rid of that tool.
What we want to figure out
is how to harness it.
And this is where the really,
really good news comes into play.
This is precisely the question
that scientists like myself
have been trying to answer
for a few decades now,
and we have learned a lot
about the science-based tools
that exist to do precisely this.
Now there are many tools out there.
I'm not going to tell you about each one,
because then we would go for 45 minutes.
But I do want to share with you
three of my favorites.
And we're going to start with language.
Right before Malala Yousafzai
became the youngest person
to ever win the Nobel Peace Prize,
for advocating for the rights
of young girls to receive an education,
She was invited onto "The Daily
Show" with Jon Stewart
to talk about her experience.
At one point during the interview,
she begins to explain
what went through her head
when she first discovered that the Taliban
were plotting to kill her.
I want to present to you
a quote right here,
of how she starts to talk
about this experience.
“I used to think that the Talib
would come and he would just kill me ...”
Nothing particularly
out of the ordinary here.
She's talking to herself
in the first person,
the way we typically think
about our lives.
But the moment she gets
to this part of the experience,
"The Taliban, they're on my doorstep,"
"they're coming to get me."
It's what is arguably the climax,
the most stressful, chatter-provoking
event you can imagine.
Once she gets to that part,
she does something kind of strange.
I'm going to show you another quote,
and I want you to look at what she says.
"I asked myself,
'What would you do, Malala?'
Then I would reply to myself,
'Malala, just take a shoe and hit him.'
But then I said, 'If you hit
a Talib with your shoe,
then there would be no difference
between you and the Talib.’”
So she starts off in the first person,
but then she switches.
She's coaching herself.
She's giving herself advice
like she would someone else,
using her name and the word "you."
In this instance, what Malala is doing,
she's using a tool that we have studied.
It is called "distanced self-talk,"
and it is useful because we human beings
are much, much better
at giving advice to other people
than we are taking our own advice.
So if you've ever felt
like a giant hypocrite,
once again, welcome
to the human condition.
There's even a name for this phenomenon.
It's called Solomon's paradox,
named after the Bible's King Solomon,
who was famous for being able
to give great advice to other people,
but when it came to his own affairs,
he stumbled mightily.
Using your own name and "you"
shifts your perspective.
It gets you to relate to yourself
like you were giving advice
to someone else,
and that makes it much, much easier for us
to wisely work through our problems.
Another tool you can use
to manage your chatter is other people.
But you have to be really careful
about who you go to for chatter support.
Many people think that the best way
to help someone else
is to let them vent their emotions,
but venting doesn't help us
work through our chatter.
I want to repeat that again,
because it's a really important take-home.
Venting doesn't help us
work through our chatter.
Venting is really useful
for strengthening the friendship
and relational bonds between people.
It is good to know that someone's there,
they're willing to take the time
to listen and empathize with you.
But if all you do is vent about a problem,
you leave that conversation,
you feel great about the person
you just spoke to,
but the chatter is still churning
because you haven't done anything
to actually address it.
The best kinds of conversations
with other people do two things.
One, the person you're talking to
does let you express your emotions.
It is important for them
to empathize with you
and validate what you're going through.
But then, once you've had an opportunity
to share your feelings,
they ideally start working with you
to broaden your perspective.
They're in an ideal position
to help you do that,
because the problem
isn't happening to them.
So think really carefully
about who your chatter advisors are.
They should be people
who both listen and advise.
That brings me to my third and final tool
that I want to share with you.
It's my favorite.
It's experiencing awe.
About 10 years ago,
scientists at Berkeley tracked a group
of military veterans and first responders
as they paddled down
Utah's majestic Green River.
They measured participants' levels
of PTSD and stress,
mental states that are
infused with chatter,
both before and after the rafting trip.
Not surprisingly, they found
that most of the participants,
their stress and PTSD levels declined
from the beginning
to the end of the experiment.
But what was surprising was the factor
that predicted those declines
in PTSD and stress.
It was participants' experience of awe.
Awe is an emotion we experience
when we are in the presence
of something vast and indescribable.
Lots of people get it
from an amazing sunset.
I'm a science geek,
so I get it when I contemplate
outer space and interplanetary travel.
We have an SUV on Mars right now,
sending us footage back of that terrain --
that is awe-inspiring to me.
When we experience this emotion of awe,
it leads to what we call
a shrinking of the self.
We feel smaller when we're contemplating
something vast and indescribable,
and when we feel smaller,
so does our chatter.
I want to wrap things up
by sharing with you
a set of observations about our,
at times, messy emotional lives
that I find myself
thinking about quite a bit.
And every time I do, it fills me
with both dread, and I find it inspiring.
Between 8,000-10,000 years ago,
our ancestors invented
the first surgical technique.
Its name was trepanation,
and what it involved doing
was drilling holes in people's skulls.
One of the reasons why this technique
was believed to be used
was to help people
manage their emotions --
big, dysregulated emotional responses.
Let the evil spirits out.
Fast-forward to 1949.
A Portuguese physician
wins the Nobel Prize
for another emotion
regulation intervention.
This one's name?
The frontal lobotomy.
We have come a long way, thankfully,
from carving holes in people's heads
and sticking ice picks
in our frontal cortices
to provide people with emotional relief.
Our toolbox of science-based skills
is vastly improved.
What we need to do a better job doing
is using these tools in our lives
and sharing them with other people.
We spend enormous amounts of resources
teaching ourselves how to communicate
more effectively with other people.
What we need to do is devote
an equivalent amount of resources
to teaching ourselves
how to communicate more effectively
with ourselves.
Thank you.
(Cheers and applause)