(Spanish) Este es una
historia de esperanza.
(English) This is a story about hope.
I grew up in Mexico City,
and as a little kid,
I had no clue about global
climate change,
the problem I'm working on
in Europe today.
But I did know air pollution.
The smog was so thick back then
that you could literally see
the air you were breathing.
Today, Mexico City's air
is dramatically cleaner.
What changed?
A combination of policy and data.
Mexico City started inspecting
vehicles every six months,
using cleaner fuels
and improving energy efficiency.
Mexico City's air pollution problem
dropped from number one in the world
to 999.
I realized firsthand how this combination
of smart policy and data
significantly improved the air in my city.
And it was clear to me:
I wanted to make a career
out of finding solutions to pollution.
I studied chemical engineering in Mexico
and went to Austin, Texas for my PhD.
And that's where I found out
about the huge climate problem
caused by methane,
which also happens to be the main
component of natural gas.
In the short term,
methane is more than 80 times
more potent than CO2
[at] trapping heat in the atmosphere.
Let's compare this year's CO2 emissions
from burning fossil fuels
to this year's methane emissions.
As you can see,
there's way, way more CO2.
But this methane
will cause as much warming
over the next 10 years
as all of that CO2.
My research team in Texas
used these newer handheld devices
to detect and quantify methane emissions
from oil and gas facilities.
This is something very important.
Once you're able to know
where the leaks are coming from,
the solutions are extremely simple.
And in most cases,
they're not expensive at all.
I realized that methane pollution
from the oil and gas industry
is so important, that five years ago,
I packed my things and moved
my entire family from Texas to Europe
to do something about it.
But does that make any sense?
I moved from Texas,
which is one of the world's major
oil and gas producing regions,
to Europe,
who is already pushing
to phase out fossil fuels.
What was I thinking,
and why was I needed in Europe?
Well let me explain.
The EU has set a very ambitious goal
to become climate neutral by 2050,
and this is part
of the European Green Deal.
Climate neutral means more than reducing
greenhouse gas emissions
within Europe's borders.
It also means not importing products
that are causing emissions elsewhere.
For example,
what if oil and gas companies
were releasing huge amounts of methane
as they drill for the oil and gas
that they want to send to Europe?
The good news is that the EU
recently passed a landmark law
to avoid that from happening.
And this is how it works.
To gain access to the European
oil and gas market,
which today remains one
of the largest in the world,
companies all around the world
are going to have to cut
their methane emissions,
just as European producers
are also required to do.
The details are still being sorted out,
but this access to market is likely
to be based on methane intensity.
That is the total amount
of methane emissions
as a percentage of production.
For example,
companies could be held
to a standard of as little as two-tenths
of one percent of their production.
As with all policies,
success depends on implementation,
and the EU methane policy
still needs to be implemented
across the 27 member states.
Now here's something really important.
How are we going to know
that oil and gas companies
all around the world
are actually complying with this?
How are we going to be able to check
that emissions are really going down,
which of course, at the end of the day,
is what we need to see?
It sounds unrealistic
that we could walk around the world
with those handheld devices,
like the ones my team was using in Texas.
But the good news
is that methane monitoring tools
have significantly evolved,
and scientists have
developed newer sensors
that work from larger distances.
First from airplanes,
and most recently from space.
MethaneSAT and other satellites
are already scanning the globe,
looking at all those different places
where oil and gas production
is taking place.
They're already delivering
accurate methane data in near-real time,
which is at the heart of making
the new EU methane strategy work.
It also explains why
the EU helped establish
the International Methane
Emissions Observatory,
where I do some of my work.
This observatory is not a telescope.
It's a global data hub
hosted by the UN Environment Programme,
and it's already bringing together
data from different satellites
and monitoring tools.
It will soon allow us to measure, monitor,
report and verify methane emissions
from different oil and gas producers
in a consistent way.
The world is watching
as this unprecedented
public access to data
promises to hold oil and gas producers
accountable for their emissions.
Data will make a difference,
just as it did in Mexico City.
And we’ve got momentum.
More than 50 companies,
representing 40 percent of global
oil and gas production,
have already committed
to reduce their own methane emissions
by almost 90 percent
by the end of this decade.
And more than 150 countries
have already signed
the Global Methane Pledge,
committing to serious methane action.
Of course, all of this commitment
and pledges need to become real.
And Europe is just the beginning.
Already, Japan and South Korea
have formed a coalition
and are also looking at methane emissions
as a condition to access their own
oil and gas import market.
In a sense,
the EU methane policy
can serve as a blueprint
as other countries and regions implement
data-driven climate action.
Even beyond methane.
For example,
we could look at the emission
footprint from other products
such as cement, steel or wood.
Or we could look at other sources
of methane beyond oil and gas,
such as agriculture and landfills.
My day-to-day work as a scientist
revolves around data,
technology and policy.
But I'm also a father of two little kids,
which makes my hope for the future
deeply, deeply personal.
Picking up the pace
at which we phase out fossil fuels
will dramatically shape
and change the world
our kids will inherit,
and we need to do this fast.
But in the meantime,
cutting methane emissions
is by far the fastest way
to slow warming today,
having an immediate impact for the people,
just as Mexico City did
with air pollution,
by using data and policy,
when I was a little kid.
(Spanish) Y es por eso
que tengo esperanza.
(English) This is why I’m hopeful,
because we're using data not only
to understand the methane problem,
but to actually fix it.
Thank you.
(Applause)